<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    <info>
		<name>Circle of Winter</name>
		<description>Druid: Circle of Winter</description>
		<author url="https://github.com/Chisatobailey/RPG-Stuff">Chisato Bailey</author>
		<update version="1.0.2">
			<file name="Druid-Winter.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Chisatobailey/RPG-Stuff/Third-Party-Additions/Druid-Winter.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Circle of Winter" type="Archetype" source="Third-Party-Additions" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_CIRCLE_OF_WINTER">
		<supports>Druid Circle</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Druids of the Circle of Winter harness the hidden powers of the frigid tundras of the world, as well as the harsh season of winter. Some of these druids make direct contact with fey courts that are associated with the winter, while others simply gain their powers due to a frozen landscape being their home.</p>
                <table>
                    <thead>
                        <tr><td>Druid Level</td><td>Feature</td></tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tr><td>2nd</td><td><em>Circle Spells, Winter Spirit</em></td></tr>
                    <tr><td>6th</td><td><em>Blizzard Cloud</em></td></tr>
                    <tr><td>10th</td><td><em>Slippery Magic</em></td></tr>
                    <tr><td>14th</td><td><em>Cold Soul</em></td></tr>
                </table>

			<div element="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_CIRCLE_SPELLS" />
			<div element="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_WINTER_SPIRIT" />
			<div element="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_BLIZZARD_CLOUD" />
			<div element="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_SLIPPERY_MAGIC" />
			<div element="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_COLD_SOUL" />
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>Druids of the Circle of Winter harness the hidden powers of the frigid tundras of the world.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_CIRCLE_SPELLS" level="2" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_WINTER_SPIRIT" level="2" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_BLIZZARD_CLOUD" level="6" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_SLIPPERY_MAGIC" level="10" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_COLD_SOUL" level="14" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Circle Spells" type="Archetype Feature" source="Third-Party-Additions" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_CIRCLE_SPELLS">
		<description>
			<p>Your link to the season of winter grants you access to certain spells. At 2nd level, you learn the frostbite cantrip, or a different druid cantrip of your choice if you already knew it. At 3rd, 5th, 7th, and 9th level you gain access to the spells listed for that level in the Circle of Winter Spells table.</p>
            <p>Once you gain access to one of these spells, you always have it prepared, and it doesn't count against the number of spells you can prepare each day. If you gain access to a spell that doesn't appear on the druid spell list, the spell is nonetheless a druid spell for you.</p> 
                <table>
                    <thead>
                        <tr><td>Druid Level</td><td>Spells</td></tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tr><td>3rd</td><td><em>Darkness, Snilloc's Snowball Swarm</em></td></tr>
                    <tr><td>5th</td><td><em>Sleet Storm, Wall of Water</em></td></tr>
                    <tr><td>7th</td><td><em>Fire Shield, Ice Storm</em></td></tr>
                    <tr><td>9th</td><td><em>Cone of Cold, Control Winds</em></td></tr>
                </table>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>Your link to the season of winter grants you access to certain spells.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_FROSTBITE" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DARKNESS" level="3" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_SNILLOCS_SNOWBALL_SWARM" level="3" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SLEET_STORM" level="5" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_WALL_OF_WATER" level="5" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FIRE_SHIELD" level="7" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ICE_STORM" level="7" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CONE_OF_COLD" level="9" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_CONTROL_WINDS" level="9" spellcasting="Druid" prepared="true" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Winter Spirit" type="Archetype Feature" source="Third-Party-Additions" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_WINTER_SPIRIT">
		<description>
			<p>At 2nd level, you can lower your body's temperature to below freezing through druidic magic. As an action, you can expend a use of your Wild Shape feature to channel the might of winter, rather than transforming into a beast form, and you gain 5 temporary hit points for each level you have in this class. While this feature is active, you gain the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
                <li>You add your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of +1) to the damage you deal with any druid cantrip or spell as additional cold damage.</li>
			    <li>Your melee weapon attacks deal an extra 1d6 cold damage to any target they hit.</li>
            </ul>
			<p class="indent">These benefits last for 10 minutes, until you lose all these temporary hit points, or until you use your Wild Shape again.</p>
			<p class="indent">Also, you are adapted to cold climates, as described in Chapter 5 of the Dungeon Master's Guide.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description>you can expend a use of your Wild Shape feature to channel the might of winter, rather than transforming into a beast form, and you gain 5 temporary hit points for each level you have in this class.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Blizzard Cloud" type="Archetype Feature" source="Third-Party-Additions" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_BLIZZARD_CLOUD">
		<description>
			<p>Beginning at 6th level, while you are affected by your Winter Spirit feature, a cloud of frost and snow billows around you, freezing your foes.</p>
            <p class="indent">As a bonus action on each of your turns, you can force one creature within 30 feet of you to make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature's movement speed is reduced by 10 feet until the end of its next turn.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus">
			<description>While you are affected by your Winter Spirit, make one creature make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. On failed save that creature's movment speed is reduced by 10.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Slippery Magic" type="Archetype Feature" source="Third-Party-Additions" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_SLIPPERY_MAGIC">
		<description>
			<p>Beginning at 10th level, your magic is permanently touched by slippery ice. When a creature fails its saving throw against a druid spell you cast that deals cold damage, it falls prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">The bonus cold damage on melee attacks granted by your Winter Spirit feature does not count as a spell dealing cold damage for this feature.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Beginning at 10th level, your magic is permanently touched by slippery ice. When a creature fails its saving throw against a druid spell you cast that deals cold damage, it falls prone. Winter Spirit's bonus damage DOES NOT count.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Cold Soul" type="Archetype Feature" source="Third-Party-Additions" id="ID_3PAD_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WINTER_COLD_SOUL">
		<description>
			<p>Starting at 14th level, your body permanently resembles a creature of snow and frost. You are immune to cold damage, and when a creature hits you with a melee attack, it takes cold damage equal to half of your druid level.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You are immune to cold damage, and when a creature hits you with a melee attack, it takes cold damage equal to half of your druid level.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>	
</elements>