<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Scholar of Magic</name>
		<description>Content created by the Chisato Bailey</description>
		<author url="https://github.com/Chisatobailey/RPG-Stuff">Chisato Bailey</author>
		<update version="0.0.1" />
			<file name="Scholar of Magic.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Chisatobailey/RPG-Stuff/Ian's-Additions/Scholar%20of%20Magic.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>
    <element name="Spell-Shaper" type="Class Feature" source="Scholar of Magic" id="ID_IANSADDITIONS_SCHOLAROFMAGIC_CLASS_FEATURE_WIZARD_SPELL_SHAPER">
		<description>
			<p>A wizard spends their life studying the ways of magic. Where others intuit the use their arcane powers or are gifted knowledge by greater forces, the wizard has spent years learning to harness and shape power into whatever form is desired. Beginning at level three, a wizard may reshape spells to meet the needs of the situation. While not all spells can, by thier nature, be manipulated in this way, many spells can be split into two or more "smaller" spells that are cast simultanously.</p>
            <p class="indent">Spells that cause damage may be reshaped a number of times equal to the number of damage dice the spell has in any even distribution. For example, a fireball spell has 8d6 damage and covers an sphere that is 20 fett in radius; this spell could be split into either 2, 4, or 8 smaller fireballs that each do less damage (4d6, 2d6, or 1d6 respectively) and affect proportionally smaller areas.</p>
            <p class="indent">The ability to shape non-damage spells is determined on a case-by-case basis. Damage and spell-area may be split, but spell effects (like causing silence or granting advantage) cannot be split.</p>
            <p class="indent">Shaping a spell has no effect on the spell's range.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You may shape many of your spells. Damaging spells may be evenly "split" into smaller versions. Non-damage spells can be reshaped, but effects like granting advantage or causing paralysis cannot be split. Spellrange is not affected by reshaping.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Warded Casting" type="Class Feature" source="Scholar of Magic" id="ID_IANSADDITIONS_SCHOLAROFMAGIC_CLASS_FEATURE_WIZARD_WARDED_CASTING">
		<description>
			<p>A wizard has learned to protect friendly tragets from the effects of thier spells. Beginning at 5th level you may shield a number of friendly targets equal to you intelligence modifier + 1 for the damage and effects of any spell you cast.</p>
            <p class="indent">You may shield {{warded:casting}} friendly targets from all damage and effects from your magic at the time of casting. This cannot be done retroactivly.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You may shape many of your spells. Damaging spells may be evenly "split" into smaller versions. Non-damage spells can be reshaped, but effects like granting advantage or causing paralysis cannot be split. Spellrange is not affected by reshaping.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="warded:casting" value="1" />
			<stat name="warded:casting" value="intelligence:modifier" />
		</rules>
	</element>
    <append id="ID_WOTC_PHB_CLASS_WIZARD">
  		<rules>
    		<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_IANSADDITIONS_SCHOLAROFMAGIC_CLASS_FEATURE_WIZARD_SPELL_SHAPER" level="3" />
			<grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_IANSADDITIONS_SCHOLAROFMAGIC_CLASS_FEATURE_WIZARD_WARDED_CASTING" level="5" />    		
  		</rules>
	</append>
</elements>